Find out what it means.
Respect is a drama, music, history film directed by Liesl Tommy.
The rise of Aretha Franklin’s career from a child singing in her
father’s church’s choir to her international superstardom.
Aretha Franklin, played by Jennifer Hudson.
C. L. Franklin, played by Forest Whitaker.
Ted White, played by Marlon Wayans.
Barbara Franklin, played by Audra McDonald.
Dinah Washington, played by Mary J. Blige.
Jerry Wexler, played by Marc Maron.
Respect is a 2021 American biographical musical drama film directed by Liesl Tommy (in her feature directorial debut),
written by Tracey Scott Wilson and Callie Khouri, based on the life of American singer Aretha Franklin.
The film stars Jennifer Hudson as Franklin, with Forest Whitaker, Marlon
Wayans, Audra McDonald, Marc Maron, Tituss Burgess, and Mary J.
Blige in supporting roles.
The film follows the first three decades of Franklin's life, from being born as a musical prodigy in an affluent African-American family, the repercussions of losing her mother at age 10 to her
arduous rise to international musical stardom, while enduring an abusive marriage, ultimately concluding with the recording of her influential live album Amazing Grace (1972).
A film on Franklin's life was in development for a long time with Franklin herself involved in the pre-production,
however the film languished in development hell for years due to lack of finding a suitable candidate.
Following release of the musical film Dreamgirls (2006), Franklin asked Hudson to play her but did
not finalize her decision until seeing her in the Broadway musical The Color Purple.
The film began production in early 2019 and had concluded by February 2020.
The film is dedicated to Franklin, who died in 2018.
After much delay and postponement, due to the burgeoning COVID-19 pandemic, Respect premiered in Los Angeles on August 8, 2021, and was released
theatrically in the United States on August 13, 2021, by United Artists Releasing, and in other territories by Universal Pictures.
The film received generally positive reviews from critics, with praise for the performances, the film's
production values, and costume design, but received criticism for its screenplay and long running time.
The film explores themes of pop singer, biography, african american
history, african american, african american musician.
The tone is emotional.